<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lawyer's advice to the devil's agents: or, Some strokes at the unfruitful works of darkness, tending to their destruction made with a weapon taken out of the armory of the Most High. By William Watson, student in law.</title>
            <author>Watson, William, student in law.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1150A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220895</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832280</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832280</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36752</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65319)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36752)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2102:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lawyer's advice to the devil's agents: or, Some strokes at the unfruitful works of darkness, tending to their destruction made with a weapon taken out of the armory of the Most High. By William Watson, student in law.</title>
                  <author>Watson, William, student in law.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. P. bookseller, at the corner of Bread-street in Cheap-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Second leaf signed A3.</note>
                  <note>Copy imperfect; print fade and tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Good and evil --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36752:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Lawyer's Advice TO THE <hi>Devil's Agents:</hi> OR, Some Strokes at the Unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Works of Darkneſs, Tending to their Deſtruction Made with a Weapon taken out of the Armory of the <hi>MOST HIGH.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>By <hi>William Watſon,</hi> Student in Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J.P.</hi> Bookſeller, at the Corner of <hi>Bread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> in <hi>Cheap-ſide.</hi> 1693.
<pb facs="tcp:36752:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:36752:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36752:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36752:3"/>
            <head>A Lawyer's Advice TO THE <hi>DEVIL's AGENTS,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>ALBEIT Men are apt to diſagree in the Performance of Holy Duties, and every one adheres firmly to that Way, which in his own Opinion ſeems beſt; yet they can very readily lay aſide all terms of diſtinction, and unanimouſly conſpire in the Commiſſion of Wickedneſs. 'Tis deemed a groſs Pollution, by many ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Zealots, to joyn with thoſe of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Tenents in the Worſhip of God; but they ſhall ſcarce make any Scruple to joyn with them in Drunkenneſs, and other Acts of Intemperance; and then, as they vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fanſie, make Atonement for it, by break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36752:4"/>forth into paſſionate Diſputations about Religion, and magnifying that, which they profeſs, above all others in the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, whilſt, poor deluded Creatures, they are acting quite contrary to the Rules of that Religion, they pretend to ſpeak ſo highly in Commendation of: which may ſerve to inform us of the great depravity of our Natures, and the abſolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Devil bears over our Faculties and Powers, when we are ſo ready to give Obedience to him, and follow his damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Dictates, and engage in his vile Service, and be ſuch forward and ambitious Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, in the Unfruitful Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which will be our utter ruine, unleſs we ſpeedily renounce them, and inſtead of delighting in, and practiſing of them, and building them up, deteſt them, and uſe our utmoſt Endeavours to pull them down and deſtroy them. And therefore 'tis mine intent to try if I can write ſomewhat that may tend to their Deſtruction, which I propoſe to do by conſidering,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> What the Unfruitful Works of Darkneſs are.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36752:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That we are not to converſe with thoſe that we know to be guilty of them, unleſs it be in order to their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Amendment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That 'tis the Duty of all tho' chiefly of Miniſters, earneſtly to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their Abolition, by a continual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of them.</p>
            <p>All thoſe Sins that are forbidden in the Goſpel, as unbecoming the pure Profeſſors thereof, and daz'ling the luſtre of their Profeſſion, which ſhould ſhine forth, and illuminate thoſe that live in the obſcure parts of the Earth, without the knowledge of God, and help to guide them to the true knowledge and Worſhip of him, may be properly called the Works of Darkneſs; becauſe they wer ethe continual Practice of thoſe wicked <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that walked in the Vanity of their Minds, and had their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings darkened, and were alienated from the Life of God, through the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that was in them, becauſe of the blindneſs of their Hearts, which were paſt feeling, and dark'ned, and they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to retain the Knowledge of God and his Laws any longer, and began to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36752:5"/>with horrible Ingratitude towards him: And even as they did not like to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain God in their knowledge, ſo he, in his juſt Anger, gave them over to a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Mind, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to a Mind void of Judgment, ſo that they were filled with all Unrighteouſneſs, and involved in the Unfruitful works, of Darkneſs; of which you have a Catalogue in the firſt Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> from the 29th Verſe to the end of the Chapter, which are theſe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, Fornication, Wickedneſs, Covetouſneſs, Maliciouſneſs, Envy, Murder, Debate, Deceil, Malignity, Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpering, Back-biting, Hating of God, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpightfulneſs, Pride, Boaſting, Inventing of evil Things, Diſobedience to Parents, Being without Onderſtanding, Covenant-breaking, Want of Natural Affection, Implacableneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmercifulneſs,</hi> and which is the higheſt Aggravation of theſe, and if there are any other ſuch like Works of Darkneſs, beſides the doing of them, <hi>the taking pleaſure in them that do them.</hi> But why are theſe Works called Unfruitful? Evil Works have fruit, as well as good ones; but here lies the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, he that does good works, labours
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36752:5"/>for himſelf, and reaps the fruit of them; but he that does evil works, labours not for himſelf, but for the Devil, and he reaps the fruit of them; and therefore they are ſaid to be unfruitful to the Perſon that does them, becauſe not he, but the Devil has the fruit of them; and he will pay him his wages, which will be everlaſting Torments in that dreadful place, where the Worm that gnaws upon the Conſcience, never dies, and the fire is not quenched. <hi>Iſa.</hi> the laſt Chapter, at the laſt Verſe. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of which ſad effect of theſe Works of Darkneſs brings me to the ſecond part of my Diſcourſe, to wit,</p>
            <p>That we are not to converſe with thoſe we know to be guilty of them, unleſs it be in order to their Converſion and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe we were ſometimes Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but now are we Light in the Lord, and know that 'tis the Will of God in Chriſt Jeſus concerning us, that we walk circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, and keep our ſelves as free, as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly we can, from all manner of Polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and endeavour both to know and do what is acceptable and well pleaſing to God,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36752:6"/>which we cannot do, if we converſe with the Wicked; I mean by converſing, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a part with them in the acts of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and running to the ſame exceſs of Riot, that they may not ſpeak evil of us, as Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners frequently do of thoſe that decline their evil Converſation, and will not be their Companions in ſin, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5. <hi>For the time paſt of our Life may ſuffice us to have wrought the Will of the Gentiles, when we walked in Laſciviouſneſs, Luſts, Exceſs of Wine, Revellings, Banqueting, and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatries. Wherein they think it ſtrange, that ye run not with them to the ſame exceſs of Riot, ſpeaking evil of you: Who ſhall give account to him that is ready to judge the Quick and the Dead.</hi> And what is more common than for a Commpany of Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, which perhaps, in politer Language, call themſelves, <hi>A Merry Society,</hi> to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid one that ſhall refuſe to go to one of the Houſes of Intemperance with them, with the reproachful Terms of being an Avaricious Perſon, and one poſſeſſed with a Spirit of Covetouſneſs in an intenſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; and that'tis not out of any diſlike or averſion to the thing, becauſe he thinks it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36752:6"/>a Sin, that he refuſes to go with them, but becauſe he is loth to part with that, which, according to their raſh and unadviſed Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, he looks upon as an ineſtimable Treaſure, and not lightly to be parted with, his Money, And thus with vain and uncharitable Arguments drawn from groundleſs ſuppoſitions, and mixed with a few deriſive Expreſſions, they ſtrengthen and confirm themſelves in their ſinful Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, and as brisk Agents for Hell, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as much as in them lies, to bring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into them alſo. But ſuppoſe this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus under Deriſion, becauſe he reſiſts theſe Solicitations to Vice, ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Covetouſneſs, it cannot properly be ſaid to be that which keeps him from this Sin, neither can he in the leaſt be ſaid to be guilty of it, by abſtaining from it; for he only is the Covetous Man, who, when it is his part to receive, receives more than he ought; and when it is his part to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſe, disburſes leſs than he ought; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that, which of right belongs not unto him, and through Oppreſſion and Injuſtice encreaſes his Subſtance; and not he that refuſes to waſte what is juſtly his own in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36752:7"/>ſinful Extravagancies. And as we ought not to ſpeak or think evilly of, or envy thoſe that by their honeſt Induſtry, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraining the waſtful Converſation of the Uagodly, improve what they have; but to praiſe and commend them, and endeavour to imitate them; ſo neither ought we to envy thoſe that enrich themſelves by Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, or chooſe any of their ways, as the Wiſe Man ſays, Prov. 3.31. <hi>Envy thou not the Oppreſſor, and chooſe none of his ways.</hi> And here thoſe evil-minded People, that are apt to envy their Neighbours, becauſe they live in better Reputation, and grow richer than they, may ſee their Folly and Sin in diſobeying God's Command. For if they get them fairly and juſtly, they are the Bleſſings of God, and 'tis his Pleaſure they ſhould have them, becauſe he knows if they will imploy them to a good uſe; and he that is angry, and through envy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines at this, repines at the Mercies of God, and is in effect angry with God, tho' he may level his Anger only at the Man envied, and vainly think it terminates in him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he gives Riches and Honour to that Perſon, which he is unwilling ſhould have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36752:7"/>them; as if he knew better how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow God's Gifts, than he himſelf does; and this is no ſmall Reflection, tho' perhaps he thinks not of it, upon God's Omniſcience, and by conſequence a moſt heinous Sin. And on the other ſide, if they get them through Diſhoneſty and Injuſtice, we are under the like Obligation not to envy them; for tho' God may ſuffer them to flouriſh for a while, yet when he ſees fit, he can ſoon ſtop their ſinful Progreſs, either by extending his pardoning and preventing Grace, if they reform, and ſincerely ask for it, or by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erting his Power and Juſtice, if they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere and continue obſtinate in their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and caſting them down into Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And the thoughts of this ſoon made the Prophet <hi>David</hi> underſtand his errour in envying the Proſperity of the Wicked, when he went into the Sanctuary to know the reaſon of it, Pſal. 73.16, 17, 18, 19. v. <hi>When I thought to know this, it was too painful for me. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil I went into the Sanctuary of God then underſtood I their end. Surely thou didſt ſet them in ſlippery places, thou caſtedſt them down into Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. How are they brought into Deſolation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36752:8"/>as in a moment? They are utterly conſumed with terrours.</hi> And moreover, a Man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not envy others, without vexing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting himſelf, he carries a Tormentour in his own Breaſt; and therefore the Holy Spirit of God ſo ſeverely declaims againſt this Sin in Sacred Writ, becauſe he would not have Men ſo fooliſhly ſinful, as to afflict and puniſh themſelves, Prov. 24.19, 20, <hi>Fret not thy ſelf becauſe of evil men, neither be thou envious at the wicked. For there ſhall be no reward to the evil Man, the candle of the wicked ſhall be put out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, We muſt not converſe with the Wicked, becauſe we ſhall not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file our ſelves, and help to ſtrengthen and confirm them in their ungodly Courſes, but entice others by our evil Examples to do the like; for evil Examples will be ſooner imitated (if we may credit daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) than good ones, eſpecially amongſt ſuch People, as this Prophane Age abounds with, which have naturally ſo ſtrong a Tendency and Inclination to wickedneſs. For if ever we had occaſion to take up the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi>'s Complaint, Chap. 4. Ver. 2. <hi>Now is the time, for by Swearing, and Lying,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36752:8"/>and Killing, and Stealing, and committing Adultery, they break out, and Blood touches Blood.</hi> The word in the Original for Blood, is ſpoken plurally <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bloods,</hi> to expreſs the great quantity that was ſpilt. And what was the cauſe of all this Blood-ſhed, but the Sin of the People? And has there not been of late, and is there not ſtill, a great deal of Blood ſpilt amongſt us that call our ſelves Chriſtians, from the ſame cauſe, when ſuch Multitudes fall by the Sword? Which we report only as matter of News, little conſidering that our wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is partly the occaſion of their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſanguinary Deaths, and that ſo far as we by our Sins have been acceſſary to their Deaths, ſo far, without a ſpeedy and ſincere asking of Pardon and Forgiveneſs, we ſhall be obliged to anſwer for them. And how can we ever expect, that God ſhould bleſs our Forces with Succeſs abroad, if we lie thus ſhamefully wallowing in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs at home? But we are ſo fooliſhly favourable to our ſelves, as to overlook this, and attribute theſe Wars and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions to other Cauſes; we know, and find there are, as in times paſt, tyrannizing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36752:9"/>and perſecuting Princes and Potentates in the World, and we fanſie they are the ſole Cauſes of them, to ſatisfie their Ambition, in enlarging their Dominions, and rendring themſelves more abſolute. 'Tis true, they are the Cauſe of Wars and Devaſtations; but 'tis only the Inſtrumental, not the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Cauſe, that is Sin. Wicked and Ambitious Princes and Rulers are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of doing miſchief, and making confuſion in the Earth, but 'tis the ſin of the People, as well as their own, that ſets them on Work. For God ſuffers wicked men to bear Rule, that they may declare themſelves Enemies to the Inhabitants of the Earth, and puniſh them for their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. And whenſoever a potent Enemy or Enemies begin to diſturb the Peace and Tranquillity of a Kingdom, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, they may aſſure themſelves, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other Reaſons they may imagine there are for it, that their ways are not pleaſing to God. For if they were, he would force them to be at Peace with them, Prov. 16.7. <hi>When a Man's ways pleaſe the Lord, he makes even his Enemies to be at Peace with him.</hi> God draws ſuch a Line of defence about
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36752:9"/>good Men, that live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that their moſt inveterate Enemies have not power to hurt them. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. <hi>And who is he that will harm you, if ye be followers of that which is good?</hi> But wicked Men lie open to the Wrath of God, and the fury and malice of their Adverfaries, and muſt never expect any real peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, unleſs they return from the errour of their ways, if the Scripture be true; for God ſays plainly, there they ſhall have no peace, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the 57th. at the teo laſt Verſes, <hi>But the wicked are like the troubled Sea, when it cannot reſt, whoſe Waters caſt up mire and dirt. There is no peace, ſays my God, to the wicked.</hi> And hence we may learn the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why we can't enjoy Peace, 'tis becauſe we don't ſeek it in the right way, we don't ſeek it in Righteouſneſs: for 'tis not a great number of Men with Swords and Spears that can procure it, without it; and if ever we would have our Nation exalted, it muſt be by Righteouſneſs, Prov. 14.34. <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs exalts a Nation, but Sin is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to any people.</hi> And what pleaſure and ſatisfaction can a conſidering perſon take in going in Company, or Converſing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36752:10"/>with the workers of Iniquity, and walking with wicked Men, whoſe very Actions car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſo much ſhame and reproach in them? What does it avail any one to be accounted a brisk Man, and of a pleaſant Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt his airy and injudicious fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinners, and ſo have their Friendſhip and Commendation; when in the mean time he does that which is hateful to God, and provokes his anger, the effect of which will be his utter overthrow, and the confuſion of his own Face? Jer. 7.19. <hi>Do they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke me to anger, ſays the Lord? Do they not provoke themſelves to the confuſion of their own Faces?</hi> But you'll ſay, the World is very full of wicked people, and therefore you muſt needs converſe with them, unleſs you go out of the World. True it is, you muſt needs converſe with them in a civil way of Commerce, and Offices of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to endeavour the reforming of them; and ſuch a Converſation the Holy Men of former Ages have been forced to have with the wicked, by living amongſt them, tho' much to their grief and Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as righteous <hi>Lot</hi> was vexed from day to day with the ungodly doings of the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36752:10"/>
               <hi>Sodomites.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>David</hi> laments it as his great Unhappineſs, that he was forced to live amongſt ungodly Men, Pſal. 120.5. <hi>Wo is me that I ſojourn in</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech; <hi>that I dwell in the Tents of</hi> Kedar. As if he ſhould have ſaid, I am ſorty that this place, which I ſought to dwell in, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it had been a godly place, ſhould, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my Expectation, and to my grief, be ſo ungodly, and that the Works of Darkneſs ſhould ſo much abound here, as the ſignification of the words <hi>Meſech</hi> and <hi>Kedar</hi> ſeems to devote unto us; for by <hi>Meſech,</hi> which ſignifies either ſeeking, or prolonging, is to be underſtood a People of <hi>Arabia</hi> that ſprang of <hi>Japhet, Gen.</hi> 10.2. where it appears, that <hi>Meſech</hi> was one of <hi>Japhet</hi>'s Sons; and by <hi>Kedar,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies blackneſs or darkneſs, is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> for <hi>Kedar</hi> is reckon'd among the Sons of <hi>Iſhmeal, Gen.</hi> 25.13. And theſe were the wicked <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that had degenerated from their pious Anceſtors, and made continual Oppoſitions againſt thoſe that were faithful, and endeavoured to retain the Piety and Integrity of their Juſt and Godly Patents, as you may ſee at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36752:11"/>the laſt Verſe of this Pſalm, <hi>I ſeek Peace, and when I ſpeak thereof, they are bent to War.</hi> But, tho' this muſt be granted as true, yet I hope we are nto under a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of joyning with them in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; we may continue in the World, and live amongſt them, without that, and muſt, if we will imitate thoſe Worthies that are now in the glorious Regions of eternal Happineſs, as the Holy Pſalmiſt, who would not ſuffer a deceitful perſon to dwell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Houſe nor a Lyar to tarry in his ſight. And the Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> that would not come into the Secrets of Ungodlineſs, or connive at it, tho' in his own Sons, as in the caſe of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> who had defiled themſelves with Blood, by killing a Man in their anger, but paſſionately crys out, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of cruelty are in their Habitations;</hi> as it is in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation; but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Inſtruments of Violence are in their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Treaties, or Aſſemblies; unleſs we chooſe rather to follow <hi>R. Salom</hi> his Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> who makes it to ſignifie Swords; then we muſt read it thus, Their Swords are Weapons of wrong, or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36752:11"/>violence. <hi>O my Soul, come not thou into their Secret, unto their Aſſembly mine honour be not thou united; for in their anger they ſlew a Man, and in their ſelf-will they digged down a wall. Curſed be their anger, for it was fierce, and their wrath, for it was cruel; I'll divide them in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ſcatter them in</hi> Iſrael, Gen. 49.5, 6, 7. And one would think you ſhould ſeek your own good ſo far, as to endeavour, in imitation of theſe pious Men, to refrain the Society of the wicked; but leſt you ſhould not, I'll enforce it with the command of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>But now I have written unto you not to keep Company; if any Man that is called a Brother,</hi> (as all Chriſtians are, and ought to live as Brethren) <hi>be a Fornicator, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, or an Idolater, or a Railer, or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner, with ſuch an one, no, not to eat.</hi> Except it be for the ſame end that our Saviour did eat with Publicans and Sinners, that is, in order to their Converſion and Amendment, and to have an opportunity of reproving of them, and contributing as much as you can to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards deſtroying the unprofitable Works of Darkneſs, which is the Duty of all, tho'
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36752:12"/>chiefly of Miniſters, as I am now to prove.</p>
            <p>'Tis not enough for us to abſTain from ſin our ſelves, and thence take occaſion to pride our ſelves in our own Righteouſneſs, and boaſt of it, and deride the Failings of others; but we muſt uſe our utmoſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to keep others out of ſin alſo, by a friendly and compaſſionate rebuking of them, whenſoever we ſee them like to fall under Temptation, according to the expreſs command of God, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy heart; thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer ſin upon him,</hi> or as the Original words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> more properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſie, That thou bear nto ſin for him, or againſt him. So that we may ſee we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not withhold reproof from Offenders, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being guilty of bearing ſin againſt them, and breaking God's Command. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon St. <hi>Jude</hi> inſtructs us how we ſhould do it, in the 22d. and 23d. Verſes of his Epiſtle, to wit, by making a difference, and calmly perſwading the more ignorant and flexible Sinners, that will hearken to one reaſoning with them for their own good,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36752:12"/>implied in thoſe Words, <hi>And of ſome have compaſſion:</hi> But to the more brutiſh and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate offenders, that deſpiſe calm and friendly Reproofs and Admonitions, you muſt uſe Arguments, that have ſomewhat of terrour mixed with them, and try if you can fear and affright them out of their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and then keep them from falling into it again, by a pious ſeverity, implied in thoſe words, <hi>And others ſave with fear, pulling them out of the fire.</hi> That is, pulling themout of Sin, which is Metaphorically and eventually called Fire, becauſe it will as certainly conſume and deſtroy the Soul (tho' for the preſent we may not be ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it) as the Fire would the Body, if it were caſt into it. And thus far private Men are obliged to reprove Sinners; as for Magiſtrates, and Men in Authority, they are obliged to go farther, and if theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods will not do, inflict puniſhment upon them; for they are the Miniſters of God, and Revengers to execute Wrath upon them that do evil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. And 'tis record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to that good Governour <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Praiſe, that he forced the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to ſerve the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. at the two laſt Verſes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36752:13"/>
               <hi>And</hi> Joſiah <hi>took away all the Abominations out of all the Countries that pertained to the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and made all that were preſent in</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ſerve, even to ſerve the Lord their God. And all his Days they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted not from following the Lord the God of their Fathers.</hi> And ſuch puniſhment would not only be a means of reſtraining the Offenders, upon whom it is inflicted, but of making others alſo beware of offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for, <hi>Smite a Scorner</hi> (ſays <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>and the Simple will beware,</hi> Prov. 19.25. And if the puniſhment that the Law ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointe for obſtinate and notorious Offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſuch as prophane Swearers, Drunkards, Adulterers, Thieves, and the like was du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and impartially inflicted, ſuch horrid Cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s and Offences would not be ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon amongſt us, as to the ſhame of our Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, which moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ely forbids them, now they are. And this war the method that <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded the Prople of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to take to put a ſtop to preſumption, the making the preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon ſuffer, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.12, 13. <hi>And the Man that will do preſumptuouſly, and will net hearken unto the Prieſt, (that ſtands to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36752:13"/>miniſter there before the Lord thy God) or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Judge, even that Man ſhall die, and thou ſhalt put away the evil from</hi> Iſrael. <hi>And all the People ſhall hear, and fear, and do no more preſumptuouſly.</hi> But alas! theſe things are now neglected, and this Duty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving ſin his been ſo long, and by ſo many ſuſpended, that 'tis commonly look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as a Soloeciſm, or fault in a Man's Manners, and a Reflection upon his Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to do it. But theſe Excuſes are to ſenſeleſs, and have ſo little weight in them, that one would think no one ſhould be ſo ſooliſh as to omit it upon this, or any ſuch like account, eſpecially if he has recourſe to St. <hi>James</hi>'s Saying, in his laſt Chapter, at the two laſt Verſes, <hi>Brethren, if any of you do err from the truth, and one convert him, let him know, that he which converts the ſinner from the errour of his way, ſhall ſave a Soul from Death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſins.</hi> And certainly 'tis better, and he gains more that ſaves a Soul from Death, that is, Damnation, which is called the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death, or Death everlaſting, as 'tis oppoſite to Salvation, which may be ſaid to be the ſecond Life, or Liſe everlaſting,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36752:14"/>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. than he that gains an Empire: For a Soul is more worth, than all the riches in the World. And now conſider, ſhall I that carry about ſo precious a Jewel, through neglect and careleſneſs, ſuffer the Devil to ſteal him away from me? What, ſpend all my time in taking care of the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Continent (I mean the Body) which will e're long be turned into Duſt, and neglect the incorruptible thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it, the immortal Spirit, which ſhall live to all Eternity? Why ſhall I ſuffer the Devil to caſt his venomous Dart through the wide Breaches, that ſin conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually makes into my Soul? Should not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> uſe my utmoſt endeavours to prevent an Enemy of wounding my fleſh, and ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> putiently permit tghe greateſt and moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Enemy, the Devil, to wound my Soul unto Death, and eternal Damnation But oh, the wonderful ſubtilty of the grand Adverſary of Mankind! He covers his may licieous deſigns under pretence of gratifying Mens Luſts, and rendering their Live more pleaſurable, and ſlily perſwading o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, that theſe things are conſiſtent with the liberty of the Goſpel, which, as the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36752:14"/>wicked <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> that great Factour of the Devil, uſed to ſay, was not intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to abridge Men of their carnal Delights and worldly Pleaſures, and telling of them, <hi>If they believe the Scriptures, and are called Chriſtians, and come now and then to their Aſſemblies, they need not be ſo ſtrict and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in their Lives, nor ſo ſolicitous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their Salvation;</hi> which according to his deceitful way of arguing, is ſo eaſily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable. And thus he hardens Men againſt the loving Calls, and earneſt Entreaties of Chriſt, in his Holy Word, and ſo draws them from ſin, to ſin, from a leſs to a greater, 'till at length he brings them to that degree of wickedneſs, as to commit ſin with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Who being paſt ſeeling, have given themſelves over unto Laſciviouſneſs, to work all unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with greedineſs.</hi> and now he thinks he has them ſecure, and if at any time their grieved Conſciences repreſent to them the miſerableneſs of their condition, and they are terrified with the diſtracting thoughts of their enſuing miſery into a weak reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of endeavouring to get out of this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable ſtate, he derides them, and tells
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36752:15"/>them, <hi>'Tis too late, the Seaſon for doing it is over, and they were as good take what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they can here, for it is in vain for them to coepect any hereafter, for Chriſt will nto accept thoſe that are ſo loaded with Iniquity as they are:</hi> But, to their unexpreſſible comfort, if they will turn from the evil of their ways, and diligently follow after Righte-ouſneſſs, they ſhall immediately hear Chriſt contradicting this Father of Lies, and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inviting of them to come unto him, and graciouſly promiſing of them reſt, Matth. 11.28. <hi>Come unto me, all ye that are heavy laden, and I'll give you reſt.</hi> And here take notice of the extraordinary Love of Chriſt, who thus kindly invites Sinners, which have been his greateſt Enemies, and deſpiſed, and diſobeyed his Holy Precepts, and ſo plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves into that trouble and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they are in no wiſe capable of getting out of, without his aſſiſtance, to come unto him for relief. Who but a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would diſoblige him, and refuſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his Invitation, when it proceeds from the pure motions of his Love towards us, and an earneſt Deſire of our being everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly happy? If one Saviour indeed did
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36752:15"/>intreat us, like many frail Mortals, ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of Empire and Greatneſs, to give Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Commands, and live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly in this preſent World, only for his own Intereſt and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, the caſe were ſomewhat altered; but 'tis purely for our good, that we may eſcape the eternal Damnation of Hell, and reign with him for ever in the Kingdom of Heaven, and behold his Glory, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. <hi>Father, I will that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory, which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me.</hi> And now what a ſtrange paſs are the people of this Impious Generation come to, that they'll rather obey the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that never did any thing for them, but always acts againſt them, as in their firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, ſo ever ſince, and continually endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours their ruine; than they will God, who created them, and redeemed them from that dreadful and everlaſting Puniſhment they were rendered obnoxious to by the Fall, by the moſt ignominious Death of his dear Son, and continually protects them with his preſerving mercy, without which, they would long ago have been conſumed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36752:16"/>and ſwallowed up in the Gulph of Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Pſal. 124.1, 2, 3. <hi>If it had not been the Lord, who was on our ſide, now may</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſay: If it had not been the Lord, who was on our ſide, when Men roſe up againſt us: Then they had ſwallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled against us.</hi> And yet the Alinrements of a Woman, that makes Profeſſion of Obſcenity, or the Incitement of a Companion in wickedneſs, ſhall ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er draw a man into Adultery, Drunkenneſs, prophaning of the Lord's Day, and other horrid Vices than the moſt tender and bleeding Diſſwaſives of a Cruciſied Jeſus ſhall keep him from them: and with their fooliſh Mirth, and vain Diſcourſes, they drown the Voice of God, crying, <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an hearth in them, that they would fear me, and keep all my Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments always, that it might be well with them, and with their Children for ever,</hi> Deut. 5.29. But if this calm, ſoft, and requeſting Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage from God will not prevail with them, to turn them from their Iniquities, they muſt expect to hear him ſpeaking to them in another ſtrain, and that very terrible, Mal. 3.5. <hi>And I'll come near to you to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36752:16"/>and I'll be a ſwift witneſs againſt the Sorcerers, and againſt the Adulterers, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt falſe Swearers, and againſt thoſe that oppreſs (or defraud) the Hireling in his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the Widow, and the Fatherleſs, and that turn aſide the Stranger from his right, and fear not me, ſays the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> God will not always wait, though he does with many obſtinate Sinners a long time, with the offers of Mercy, if they will not accept it in that time and manner, that he thinks fit to beſtow it upon them; for a Man may defer making his Reconciliation to God ſo long, 'till he may withdraw his aſſiſting Grace from him, and let angry Juſtice take place of abuſed Mercy, and then it can never be done, but he muſt be content to be amongſt thoſe, whoſe end is Deſtruction, and may ſadly apply that Saying of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.42. to his own particular caſe, <hi>If thou hadſt known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy Day, the things which belong unto thy Peace! But now they are his from thine eyes.</hi> And you may ſee an Example of it in wicked <hi>Eſau,</hi> who could find no place of Repentance. though he ſought it carefully with Tears, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17. And if a Man
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36752:17"/>did but ſeriouſly conſider, to what a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious height of wickedneſs the World <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> now grown, he may have juſt cauſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire at the great patience of the Almighty in bearing with ſuch groſs Impieties, and no drawing the Sword of his Juſtice, and cutting the prophane Committers of them from the Face of the Earth; for they are grown more impious than the Idolatrous Ancient of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for they did their wickedneſs in the dark, every Man in the Chambers of his Imagery, for they ſay, <hi>The Lord ſees us not, the Lord has forſaken the Earth;</hi> and ſo endeavoured to conceal it at leaſt they fanſied it would not be take ſo much notice of by the Almighty, <hi>Ez,</hi> 8.12. but theſe are more impudent, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the moſt heinous ſins in the face of the whole World, and are ſo far from being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, that they glory in it, and think it an addition to their Reputation, which they fooliſhly imagine is highly increaſed by approving themſelves men of greater A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities in Acts of Debauchery than other men: Otherwiſe, why do our immoderate Drinkers take ſuch pleaſure, and ſo applaud themſelves, in that they are able to drink
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36752:17"/>down others of more infirm Bodies and weaker Brains, and not only triumph over them for the preſent, but frequently report it afterwards, as if it tended to their credit, with a kind of rejoycing? But let them know themſelves to be wicked in ſo doing, and that the rejoycing of the wicked is not good; and ſure I am, that when Men thus rejoyce and glory in their ſin, they glory in their ſhame, as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.19. And as they thus deal with God in wickedneſs, ſo muſt they expect he will deal with them in fury, <hi>Ez.</hi> 8. at the laſt Verſe, <hi>Therefore will I alſo deal in fury; mine eye ſhall not ſpare, neither will I have pity; and though they cry in mine Ears with a loud voice, yet will I not hear them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But have not thoſe whoſe profeſſion obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them to be the moſt earneſt and careful Reprovers of Sin, been defective in it, and ſo permitted this Flood of Wickedneſs to flow in upon us with greater violence than otherwiſe it would? We will ſee what their Office is, and how they diſcharge it, and we ſhall ſoon be reſolved: They are ſet as Watchmen to the People, and are to cry aloud and ſpare not, and to lift up
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36752:18"/>their voice like Trumpets, and ſhew the people their Tranſgreſſions, and the Houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> (that is, the whole Family of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers) their ſins, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.1. And this they do in alarming Sinners, though with too much coldneſs and indifferency, ſome of them, from the Pulpit; but this is not all they ought to do, for if they find that ſin grows ſo ſtrong amongſt their Auditors, that publick Preaching will not ſuppreſs it, they might do well to ſpeak unto them by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſive Letters, if they are capable of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and underſtanding of them: but if they are of ſo perverſe and reprobate a mind that they will not do; then let them try the laſt Remedy, and have frequent perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal conference with them, and not ſuffer ſin, the Devil's Standard bearer, to diſplay his triumphant Banners in the hearts of their people without controul. But eaſe and idleneſs will ſoon frame excuſes for them, and tell them, this is the ready way to be accounted buſie impertinent perſons, and become the common objects of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and deriſion amongſt their hearers, and what is this, but under colour of being afraid of offending their Hearers, being
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36752:18"/>unwilling to be too buhe for God, and the good of their Souls, and diſobeying the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Apoſtle, who bids them <hi>be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long ſuffering and doctrine?</hi> 2 Tim. 4.2. For I would fain know how that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter keeps a diligent watch over the Souls of his Congregation, as he that muſt give an Account, when he knows any one of them to live in a continual courſe of Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Drunkenneſs, and other damnable ſins, and does not follow him earneſtly with private reproof, when he may better ſtate his caſe to him, than in a publick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe; although, I think, Divines might deſcend more to particular Caſes in their publick Preachings, than many of them do if they did not aim more at a learned and exact Method, than a plain edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe. For why ſhould not a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, that is preaching againſt any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſin, that he knows one Man in his Congregation to be more addicted to than any of the reſt, ſpeak plainly to him, as the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi> and ſay, Thouart the Man; for ſome muſt be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved openly, that others may fear, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36752:19"/>20. <hi>Them that ſin, rebuke before all, that others alſo may fear.</hi> But what if he ſhould take offence at this, and grow more obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in his ſinful Practices? Then take a convenient opportunity of diſcourſing with him in private about it, and calmly ſhew him the reaſonableneſs and neceſſity of it, and try whether Arguments drawn from the Mercies of God, which he thus ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſes, will work him into a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and if that will not do, make for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible application of the Threats of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt obſtinate Sinners, and raiſe an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of Hell in his Breaſt; wound his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to the quick, and dreſs the Wounds with Fire and Brimſtone, and never ſuffer him to be at reſt 'till he reforms; ye that make mention of the Lord, keep not ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and give him no reſt, till he eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, and 'till he make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, every one's particular Congregation) a praiſe in the Earth. You have Inſtruments put into your hands for the doing of it if you would make good uſe of them, The Word of God, which is quick and powerful, and ſharper than any two-edged Sword, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing even to the dividing aſunder of Soul
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36752:19"/>and Spirit, and of the Joynts and Marrow, and is a dncerner of the Thoughts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Heart; and would ſoon ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, if it were well applied, between ſin and the ſinner. But many Paſtors now-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days, are too much like thoſe blind Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> inveighs againſt, Chap. the 56th. at the three laſt Verſes, to do this; <hi>His Watchmen are blind; they are all ignorant, they are all dumb Dogs, they cannot bark; ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber. Yea, they are greedy Dogs which can never have enough, and they are Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards that cannot underſtand; they all look to their own way, every one for his gain, from his Quarter. Come ye, ſay they, I will fetch drink; and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abundant.</hi> And theſe are they, againſt whoſe evil Example the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle forewarns us, when he bids us feed the Flock of God, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind, 1 Pet. 5.2, 3. <hi>Feed the Flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof not by conſtraint, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind: Neither as being Lords over God's
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36752:20"/>Heritage; but being Exampes to the Flock.</hi> But now Men ſeem to endeavour rather to feed themſelves of the flock, than to feed it, elſe, why ſhould any one deſire two or three Benefices, when through infirmity of Body, weakneſs of mind, or both, he is not able to ſerve one, as he ought? And I doubt the very end in taking to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in ſome is not good; that 'tis rather to get wherewithal to live after the Luſts of their corrupt Fleſh, than to do God Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice by inſtructing the people; otherwiſe I cannot ſee how they ſhould be ſo exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Wickedneſs inſtead of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and live ſuch looſe and debauched Lives as they do, and not regard God, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of their ſpoiling his Tabernacle, and deſtroying his Church, and telling them, for their puniſhment, they ſhall not proſper, and their Flocks ſhall be (as they are already too much) ſcattered, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 20, 21. <hi>My Tabernacle is ſpotled, and all my Cords are broken; my Children are gone forth of me, and they are not; there is none to ſtretch forth my Tent any more, and to ſet up my Curtains. For the Paſtors are become brutiſh, and have not ſought the Lord; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36752:20"/>they ſhall not proſper, and all their flocks ſhall be ſcattered.</hi> Others there are, who ſeem to be a little more conſcious of their ways, and abſtain from theſe publick and ſcandalous Enormities, and are apt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of their Congregations ſcattering, and going from them, and running into Errours; but they don't take a right Method to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it: For, if they know that thoſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, to which they adjoyn themſelves, are erroneous either in their Doctrine, or their Practices, why don't they go to them, or ſend for them, and ſhew them their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours? No, 'tis beneath them to enter into a Diſputation with an ignorant Mechanick, he is not capable of judging of the ſtrength of an Argument.</p>
            <p>Sure he muſt be a very ignorant perſon, that is not capable of judging when he is ſhewed to be in an errour from plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-proof, which is the only Fountain, from whence a Divine ought to draw his Arguments, for convincing of Gain-ſayers. And in truth 'tis a lamentable thing for a Miniſter to ſuffer any one in his Pariſh to live in Superſtition and Errour, and not ſhew him it, and endeavour by frequent
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36752:21"/>converſing with him, and adviſing of him, to work him out of it, becauſe he would be accounted a meek and quiet Man: Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs indeed is a very excellent Vertue, and our bleſſed Saviour was very meek in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and when he was reviled, he reviled not again; yet he was as fierce as a Lyon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin and errour, and in defending his People from the Snates of the Devil, and his Emiſſaries; and therefore called the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> Rev. 5.5. A Miniſter may do his Duty in this particular, as well as in any other, without loſing the Character of a meek and peaceable perſon, and ſhall be better eſteemed of by all good Men, if he does it, than if he omits it, and be ſo accounted of as the Miniſter of Chriſt, and Steward of the Myſteries of God, when they ſee that he is faithful in the buſineſs, whereunto he was called, and as an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Servant to his Maſter Chriſt, is careful and exact in the diſcharge of his Duty. But I ſuppoſe I may give a more probable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their neglect in this point, for ought I know they may be afraid that theſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Mechanicks, as they call them, that ſeek inſtruction elſewhere, though they are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36752:21"/>not ſo well skilled in Languages, and have not read ſo many old Moth-eaten Authors; yet they may be almoſt as well acquainted with the Scriptures, by making them their daily Study, as they themſelves are; and if they cannot free themſelves from thence from the errours and miſtakes, that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged againſt them; yet they may be able to prove, that they, to their great ſhame and reproach, do frequently contradict their Doctrine by their Practices, and lead Lives diſagreeable to the true Apoſtolical Rules; which they might do prudently to conſider of, and try if they can retrieve their ſinking Reputation, by keeping the Law of Truth in their Mouths, and not ſuffering falſhood or contradiction to be found in their Lips or Lives, by walking with God in Peace and Equity, and in turnig many away from Iniquity, and in ſtriving conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to ſubdue Sin, and make Holineſs, which is now much eclipſed, and in very great decay, to revive, and ſhine more brightly amongſt us; leſt they fall deeper, than they are ſome of them already fallen, under that ſevere Accuſation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Malachi</hi> againſt the Prieſts of his time,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36752:22"/>when he firſt told them what their duty was, and then accuſed them for neglecting of it, Mal. 2.7, 8, 9. <hi>For the Prieſts Lips ſhould keep knowledge, and they ſhould ſeek the Law at his Mouth; for he is the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Lord of Hoſts. But ye are departed out of the way; ye have cauſed many to ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the Law,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ye have cauſed many to fall in the Law) <hi>ye have corrupted the Covenant of Levi, ſays the Lord of Hoſts. Therefore have I alſo made you contemptible and baſe before all the People, according as ye have not kept my ways, but have been partial</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and have accepted Faces) <hi>in the Law.</hi> And yet for all this, they keep up to their former ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and rigidity, in retaining things in the Church that are indifferent, and meerly ceremonial, and in no wiſe eſſential to the Worſhip of God, to the great hinderance of peace and unity amongſt us, in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of the Almighty, under pretence 'tis for the grandeur and dignity of the Church; but I ſuppoſe 'tis more for the advantage of the Church-men, that by keeping others out they may have the whole Harveſt to themſelves, and becauſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36752:22"/>they are afraid, that by being more painful in the work of the Miniſtery, and leading Lives more ſtrict and conſcientious, they would be a reproach to theirs, which are commonly more idle, looſe, and prophane. And what tho' the Worſhip of the <hi>Jews</hi> was by God's allowance attended with a pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Train of Ceremonies, to raiſe among the People the greater eſteem of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they depended on Chriſt only in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, whereas we have him in poſſeſſion (I mean in his Goſpel) and therefore we have not the like need of them, that they had; eſpecially if we conſider what a vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different, and contrary effect they have upon us: For as they ſtrengthened and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited them in the Worſhip of God, they weaken and diſunite us. And certainly God takes not pleaſure in Ceremonies, but in ſincerity of Obedience. And therefore when terms of reconciliation in this point are propoſed, they are much to blame that keep not cloſe to the Scripture in their Reaſonings, but by quoting of Councils, Fathers, and School men, and by learned and ſubtile ways of arguing, and by multiplying Diſtinctions, puzzle and weary
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36752:23"/>their Opponents, and drown them with a flood of words, and then revile them, and triumph over them, as if they had got the Cauſe; and ſo rather than they will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a diminution to their Learning and Judgments, and loſe the repute of being able to worſt thoſe they argue againſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there they have right on their ſider, or no, they will imprudently keep a foot at leaſt, if not widen our Diffeences ſtill, though to the offence of their Brethren. But this being an occaſion of offence to their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. by refuſing to comply with them in things indifferent, is not to imitate, but to act quite contrary to the Apoſtle St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> who ſiad, <hi>If his eating fleſh did make his Brother to offend, he would eat not more whilſt the world ſtood,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. at the laſt Verſe. He would not let his weak Brother, for whom Chriſt died, periſh through his knowledge. And ſpreſume we may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably infer from hence, That if any Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he wore, when he inſtructed the people, had been offenſive to them, and likely to have occaſioned their depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him, he would not have refuſed to have laid it aſide, and removed their
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36752:23"/>Scruple. For he commands the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to give offence to none, according to his own Example, in things indifferent, I <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. at the two laſt Verſes, <hi>Give none of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God: Even as I pleaſe all men in all things</hi> (meaning indifferent things) <hi>not ſeeking mine own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be ſaved.</hi> 'Tis ſtrange there ſhould be ſuch a diſagreement amontſt us in matters of Religion; did we not all ſpring from the ſame root? Have we not one Father? Has not one God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us all? And have we not one Saviour, one Holy Ghoſt, one Hope, Faith, and Baptiſm? And as Chriſt is our Head, and we his Body, by the like proportion as the Members of a natural Body, tend all to the mutual Decency, Service, and Succour of the ſame Body, ſo we ſhould do one for another, to make up the myſtical Body of Chriſt, 1 Cor. 12.27. <hi>Now ye are the Body of Chriſt, and Members in particular,</hi> And what is the reaſon we don't do this? 'Tis becauſe we are Carnal, 1 Cor. 3.3. <hi>For ye are yet carnal; for whereas there is among you envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions, are ye
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36752:24"/>not carnal, and walk as men?</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and walk according to Man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not according to God) And the only way to remedy this, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more ſpiritual, and to endervour to abound as much in the fruits of the Spirit, as we have hitherto in the fruits of the fleſh; and then we ſhall not be ſo deſirous of vain Glory, nor ſo apt to provoke and envy one another: But 'tis to be hoped one party would as readily aſcend, as the other ſhould deſcend, and ſo they would meet, and agree in the mean; which they muſt do, if ever there be a laſting Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation amongſt them: For both Parties are in fault, the Diſſenters in requiring too much alteration in our publick way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; the Chruch of <hi>England</hi> in being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to allow enough. And thus having ſhewn the failings of your Paſtors and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters towards you, that I may not be liable to an Accuſation of partiality, and beſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have done it out of any prejudice towards them. I ſhall now ſhew yours to them, that both Prieſt and People may ſee their Errours, and forſake them, leſt as they are alike in their offences; ſo alſo they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36752:24"/>ſhould be alike in their Puniſhments, as the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſays in his 4th. Chapter at the 9th, and 10th. Verſes, <hi>And there ſhall be like People, like Prieſt, and I will puniſh them for their ways, and reward them their doings. For they ſhall eat, and not have enought; they ſhll commit Whoredom, and ſhall not encreaſe, becauſe they have left off to take heed to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Firſt, You are apt raſhly to cenſure your Miniſters, and affirm that they do not take pains enough in their Stations, and therefore do not Preach to you with that livelineſs and earneſtneſs that otherwiſe they might; but don't conſider that you your ſelves are in a great meaſure the occaſion of it. For what can more diſcourage a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, than, when he has preached ten or twenty years againſt groſs and heinous ſins, to find them reign as much or more in his Congregation, than when he firſt came to it, and that almoſt all his Labour is loſt, as to the reforming of his ſinful Hearers, and his Doctrine deſpiſed and neglected? Is not this the way to help to ſtop and hinder the Utterance of your Miniſters, inſtead of praying that it may be given to them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36752:25"/>to the Apoſtle's Command, that they may be bold to make known the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpel? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> the laſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 18, 19, 20th. Verſes. <hi>Praying always with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirits and watching thereunto with all Perſeverance, and Supplication for all Saints, and for me, that utterance may be given unto me that I may open my mouth hodly, to make known the Myſtery of the Goſpel: For which I am and Embaſſadour in Bonds, that therein I may ſpeak boldly, as I ought to ſpeak.</hi> And if St. <hi>Paul</hi> had occaſion for the Prayers of the People to enable him to ſpeak as he ought; much more occaſion have the Paſtors of our times, who are far inferiour to him in gifts and knowledge: But truly if they could not in ſome meaſure ſpeak as they ought, without them, I know not when they would; for I doubt many People ſeldom think of praying that their Teachers may be able to teach them as they ought, much leſs do it. But let them know that their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting or neglecting of it, does not in any wife make it ceaſe to be their Duty.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:36752:25"/>
            <p>Secondly, You have not that Eſtimation for them that you ought, but generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn and deſpiſe their Office and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſet leſs by them tha the temporal Phyſician, and the Profeſſor of the Law; for, though you'll adviſe with the one, when your Bodys are arreſted by a dangerous Diſeaſe, and if your Title to your Eſtate be any way ſcrupled, you will not be any means omit conſulting the other; yet you think it beneath you to adviſe with your Miniſter, though your Souls are in danger of periſhing throgh Sin, and your Title to Heaven be never ſo doubtful, and will imprudently rely upon your own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this reſpect, although it is a matter of the greateſt moment t' ye in the whole World, and that which you are highly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to be as well aſſured of, as poſſible yo can: And hereupon 'tis you are ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly exhorted by the Apoſtle to make your Calling and Election ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Wherefore the rather, Brethren, give diligence to make your calling and election ſure.</hi> But this may ſerve to inform us, and that much to our diſgrace, that we are generally more careful in the preſervation of our Bodies
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36752:26"/>and Eſtates, which are mortal, and periſh in the very uſing, than we are of our Souls, which are immortal, and can never ceaſe to be, either happy, or miſerable. And hence it comes to puſs that your Miniſters are not worthy to be ſent for in your ſickneſs, no, not in the greateſt extremity of it, even at the point of Death; but perhaps you think 'tis their Duty to come: I ſhall not ſay 'tis not, for I ſuppoſe 'tis, if they know it; but I am ſure if they do not come without ſending for, 'tis your Duty to ſend for them, <hi>Jam</hi> 5.14, 15. <hi>Is any ſick among you? let him call for the Elders of the Church, and let them pray over him, anointing him with Oil in the Name of the Lord: And the prayer of faith ſhall ſave the ſick, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him up, and if he has committed Sins, they ſhall be forgiven him.</hi> But this Text of Scripture is ſome what intricate, and the true meaning of it may not eaſily be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by a vulgar Capacity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not think it impertinent a little to explain it. <hi>Elders</hi> is a Title of Dignity rather than of Age, and there were two ſorts of them, the one took care of the Government and Behaviour of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36752:26"/>only, the other beſides that did pray and preach to them alſo: And both theſe Orders were very honourable, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the ſaying of the Apoſtle, 1 Tim. 5.17. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worthy of double Honour, eſpecially they which labour in the Word and Doctrine.</hi> But methinks I hear ſome conceited ignorants ſay, How ſhall any one ſend for the Elders, there are none in our Church? But that is their miſtake: All Eccleſiaſticks compleated in ſacred Orders, by what Titles ſoever they are dignified, or diſtinguiſhed, are Elders; and ſo were the very Apoſtles al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as they frequently ſtile themſelves, 1 Pet. 5.1. <hi>The Elders</hi> (that is, thoſe that are Paſtors, and have the care of the Church, as you may eaſily gather from the following Verſe) <hi>which are among you I exhort, who am alſo an Elder.</hi> But then you'll ſay, Why don't we call them ſo? We do in effect ſo call them; for our word <hi>Prieſt</hi> is the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal word for Elder, which is I <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, contracted, or ſhortened. And as for the word <hi>Biſhop,</hi> which many ſeem to take of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at, it is derived from the <hi>Saxon</hi> word <hi>Biſceop,</hi> and that from the <hi>Greek</hi> word
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36752:27"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the very Title by which thoſe of the higheſt Dignity in the Church were ſtiled in the Apoſtles days, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7. and ſigniſies an <hi>Inſpector,</hi> or him to whom the Over-ſight of the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs; and this Name I take to be given to them for reaſon, becauſe, as it was the Office of him that was called by this Name among the Heathens, to ſee that their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Food was duly adminiſtred to them; ſo it is the Office of a Biſhop to take care that Chriſtians may have their ſpiritual food duly adminiſtred to them: And though ſome, that delight in Novelties, chooſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to call thoſe that officiate in their Churches, Miniſters, and Superintendents, than Prieſts and Biſhop are the ſame thing, only Prieſt and Biſhop are derived from <hi>Greek</hi> Fountains, which is the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Language of the New Teſtament, and Miniſter and Superintendent, the one is a <hi>Latin</hi> word, and the other derived from a <hi>Latin</hi> word; and if they abhor the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, ſo much as they pretend, I wonder why they ſhould have ſuch an eſteem for its Language, as rather to let it enter into their Church by their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36752:27"/>Eccleſiaſtical Titles, than the <hi>Greek,</hi> or words derived from it, which is the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage Apoſtolical. And truly thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons act very imprudently, that raiſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies about, and contend againſt, and hate the innocent Names, by which thoſe of the Holy Function are diſtinguiſhed, for the Offences of the Perſons called by them; for they neither occaſion their offending, neither can they reſtrain them from it. And whereas mention is here made of the ſick's being ſaved, and raiſed up, and his ſins forgiven, through the Bleſſing of the Lord upon the Prayer of Faith; we muſt underſtand, that the Elders in the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Days, were endued with miraculous Gifts, as the Apoſtles themſelves were, ſo as to be able through the ſtrength of their Prayers and Exhortations to heal the ſick, and take away the principal cauſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers from them, which was their ſins, by procuring for them the forgiveneſs of them. And the anointing with Oyl was uſed as the ſign of this miraculous Gift of healing, and obtaining the forgiveneſs of ſick Men's ſins by their Prayers, which our Church has very judiciouſly laid aſide, as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:36752:28"/>not neceſſary, ſeeing <hi>healing,</hi> the thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by it, as well as all other miraculous Gifts ceaſed, when the end, for which they were deſigned, which was a Confirmation and Eſtabliſhment of the Goſpel ſufficient for its ſupport, encreaſe, and further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation without them, was accompliſhed: which was, as ſome Church-Hiſtorians tell us, about the end of the third, or ſhortly upon the beginning of the fourth Century, which is about thirteen hundred years ſince. And thoſe ſuperſtitious perſons that ſtill make uſe of this anointing the Sick with Oyl, as the Elders in the Primitive times did, unleſs they could in the like miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous manner perform the ting ſignified by it, and reſtore them to Health, and obtain the Remiſſion of their Sins, without the uſe of other means, as they did, do but ſhew their folly, and render themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to Ridicule and Deriſion amongſt People of Underſtanding, that have not renounced their Senſes, and imprudently yielded themſelves up to fraudulent perſons Impoſitions, and captivated their Belief to the Conduct of Impoſtors and Deceivers, which are forced to pretend to theſe, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36752:28"/>ſuch like wonderful performances, to bear up their Reputation amongſt thoſe they have ſo far deluded, as in part to ſatisfie their Ambition and Covetouſneſs by making Merchandize of them, as the Apoſtle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told of them, 2 Pet. 2.3. <hi>And through Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs ſhall they with feigned words make Merchandize of you,</hi> (but let them read the remaining part of the Verſe, and ſee how faſt Judgment and Damnation are coming upon them for it) <hi>whoſe Judgment now of a long time lingers not, and their Damnation ſlumbers not.</hi> And theſe are the evil Men, that by groſly abuſing their power in the Church, have made the People unwilling to allow the Reformed Churches ſo much power as Chriſt has given them, and will ſcarce be induced to believe that they ought, or that 'tis to any purpoſe for them, if their Conſciences are loaded and diſquieted through any grievous Crimes they have been guilty of, to make confeſſion of them to their Paſtors and Teachers, and ask their Advice, and deſire them to put them in the beſt and moſt effectual method towards the getting of their Grief removed, and their ſins pardoned, and that they would help
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:36752:29"/>and aſſiſt them, by beſtowing their ſervent Prayers upon them, towards the doing of it, although the Apoſtle expreſly commands us to confeſs our Faults one to another, and pray for one another that we may be heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16. and them gives an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging reaſon drawn from the powerful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Prayer; <hi>The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous Man avails much.</hi> And if we are obliged to confeſs our faults one to another, and pray one for another towards the healing of them, much rather to the Miniſter, that he may pray for us towards the healing of our Offences. Nor does the true and faithful Miniſter's power end here. in hearing the Confeſſions of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and praying for them; but it extends further, and authorizes him, when he finds the Offender has performed thoſe acts of Repentance, which God's Holy Word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, to apply the merciful Promiſes of God to repenting Sinners, in the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their ſins, unto him, and declare his Crimes pardoned, through the great Mercies of God, and the Merits of his dear Son Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo reconcile him to God, as having received from him the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36752:29"/>of Reconciliation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18. <hi>And all things are of God, who has reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us to himſelf by Jeſus Chriſt, and has given to us the Miniſtery of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Some of you think them bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome, and that their allowance is too great, and above their Deſerts; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon argue that Tithes are not of Divine Inſtitution, and that you are no where commanded to pay them in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But in what part of the ſame Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament are you forbidden to pay them? And although they are not ordained in expreſs words in the Goſpel by Chriſt; yet he has ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of it, 1 Cor. 9.13, 14. <hi>Do ye not know that they which miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple? And they which wait at the Altar, are partakers with the Altar. Even ſo has the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> And can you find out any better way of raiſing wherewithal they may live upon, than by giving of them Tithes? And this I may ſay
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36752:30"/>for the Lawfulneſs and Authority of them, that our Saviour told the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> that they ought to pay them; which I ſuppoſe he would not have done, if he had intended to aboliſh them, and that they ſhould not have been paid under the Goſpel, Matt. 23.23. <hi>Woe unto you Scribes and Phariſees, Hypocrites; for ye pay Tithe of Mint, and Aniſe and Cummin, and have omitted the weightier matters of the Law, Judgment, Mercy, and Faith; theſe ought you to have done, and not to leave the other undone.</hi> And here obſerve that this Woe is not denounced againſt them, becauſe of their exactneſs in paying Tithes, even to the very Herbs; but becauſe of their Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, in not being as exact in things of greater concern, as making right Judgment in deciding of Controverſies, ſhewing Mercy, and relieving the oppreſſed, and being as faithſful in the performance of their Promiſes, as they were in paying of Tithes, both which ought to have been done with the like exactneſs. And this may ſerve to admoniſh us, as well as let us know that our Saviour allowed of paying Tithes in his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36752:30"/>time, againſt the folly and errour of ſuch Hypocrites, as will be very exact and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in things of leſs moment, and remiſs and careleſs, and apt to paſs over thoſe things that are of far greater concern. And the reaſon of the Apoſtle's not requiring Tithes, may be this , becauſe they would not hinder the progreſs of the Goſpel, by giving them the leaſt occaſion of thinking they preached it more for their own profit and advantage, than for their Good: And hereupon the Apoſtle ſays, he wrought with his own hands that he might not be chargeable to any of them; not but that he had power to forbear working, and live by preaching the Goſpel, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but he did not uſe this power, but rather ſuffered all things, leſt he ſhould make his Doctrine the leſs eſteemed, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 19.12. <hi>If others be Partakers of this power over you, are not we rather? Novertheleſs, we have not uſed this power, but ſuffer all things, leſt we ſhould hinder the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> But if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of our Times were obliged to do the like, we ſhould ſoon have but mean preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36752:31"/>and a very ignorant and contemptible Miniſtery: and inſtead of anſwering the Controverſies and Objections of our learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Adverſaries with our Tongues or Pens, we muſt anſwer them with our Swords, which I think will hardly be allowed to be the true Evangelical, or Goſpel-way of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of them. For it pleaſed God to furniſh the Apoſtles with extraordinary means to preach and declare his Will; ſo that if they were diſpoſed to ſupply their Neceſſities by any ſervile Occupation (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did by Tent making. <hi>Act</hi> 18.3.) it could not any ways diſinable them for teaching and inſtructing the People; for what they were to ſpeak and teach was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into them, without any pains or ſtudy of theirs, in that very hour, in which they were to ſpeak it, Matt. 10.19. <hi>But when they deliever you up, take no thought how or what ye ſhall ſpeak; for it ſhall be given in that ſame hour what ye ſhall ſpeak.</hi> But God has thought fit to let ordinary means take place in theſe latter Ages, and Men muſt or ought at leaſt, by continual ſtudy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry to qualifie themſelves for the Work
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36752:31"/>of the Miniſtery; and muſt be ſupported of thoſe they inſtruct, in the doing of it, and this they ought to do freely, and not to count it a great thing, but moſt reaſonable, that they ſhould reap their carnal things, which ſow to them ſpiritual things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. <hi>If we have ſowen unto you ſpiritual things, is it a great thing if we ſhall reap your carnal things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, If they inveigh ſharply againſt ſin, and a little terrifie you with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughts of Hell and Damnation, you are ready to exclaim againſt the ſeverity of their Doctrine, and to ſay, 'Tis the ready way to preach you to Deſperation; but this is your miſunderſtanding of them, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to preach you to deſperation in that ſenſe you take the Word in, that is, ſo as to make you deſpair of attaining Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but only to make you deſpair of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of it in the condition many of you are now in, (which ſort of Deſperation may be a means of putting you into the way of Salvation) for to what purpoſe is it for you to hope to go to Heaven, whilſt you continue in thoſe ſins you are told
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:36752:32"/>from God's Word will keep you thence? 'Tis impoſſible for you that are Drunkards, Thieves, Swearers, and Adulterers, and are in the way to everlaſting Deſtruction, without a ſpeedy Reformation and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it the Kingdom of Heaven; unleſs you can get the Decrees of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty revoked, and make the Apoſtle a Liar, for he expreſly ſays you ſhall not, 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. <hi>Know ye not that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God? Be not deceived; neither Fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor Eſſomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, nor Abuſers of themſelves with Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, nor Extortioners ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> And again, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. having ſummed up the Works of the Fleſh, he ſays, <hi>of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in time paſt, that they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Read the Verſes, and ſee what the Works of the Fleſh are, <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſiviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Idolatry, Witchcraſt, Hatred, Variance, Emulations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:36752:32"/>Envyings, Murders, Drunkenneſs, Revellings, and ſuch like;</hi> and know aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, that if you are guilty of any of them, you muſt forthwith ask pardon of God for it, and forſake them, otherwiſe they will keep you from the Seat of the Bleſſed. Nor is it enough for a Man to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from theſe groſſer Sins towards the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caping of everlaſting miſery, but he muſt abſtain from all ſins, as much as is poſſible, though never ſo ſmall; for the leaſt ſin is in it ſelf damnable: and therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle commands us to abſtain from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evil, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. And if your Miniſters ſhould paſs this lightly over, and preach unto you ſmooth things; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe and delight your Fancies, and not rough and ſevere things to diſturb and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken your Conſeiences, and diſquiet you in the enjoyment of your ſeemingly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſins, they would do the Work of the Lord deceitfully, and ruine you, and pull down a Curſe upon themſelves, and your Blood would be required at their hands as God tells the Prophet <hi>Ezlekiel,</hi> that as the Blood, that was loſt in the Land by the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:36752:33"/>Sword, through the neglect of the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Watchman, in not warning the people of their Enemies coming, ſhould be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at his hands, ſo he would require the Blood of thoſe that periſhed in their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, through his neglect in warning of them at his hands, whom he had made a ſpiritual Watchman. <hi>So thou, O Son of Man, I have ſet thee a Watchman unto the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>therefore thou ſhalt hear the Word at my Mouth, and warn them from me. When I ſay unto the wicked, O wicked man, thou ſhalt ſurely die; if thou doeſt not ſpeak to warn the wicked from his way, that wicked man ſhall die in his Iniquity; but his Blood will I requie at thine hand. Nevertheleſs if thou warn the wicked of his way to turn from it; if he do not turn from his way, he ſhall die in his iniquity; but thou haſt delivered thy Soul.</hi> Ezek. 33.7, 8, 9. So you ſee the great neceſſity that lies upon them of uſing ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying Diſcourſes to you, both in reference to you and themſelves; if you would but once renounce your affections to Sin, and endeavour to arrive to ſome perfection
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36752:33"/>of Holineſs in the fear of God, no doubt, they would ſoon turn the courſe of their Preaching, and inſtead of talking of Hell and everlaſting Burnings, ſpeak to you of nothing but the Gracious Promiſes that are made to you, and giving you the beſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, that, according to their moſt deliberate Conceptions of it, they could, of Heaven, and the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Joys thereof: which are ſo great, that there are no earthly Joys, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſhould much exceed that of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> at the Coronation of their Peaceable King, which, (as, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the original words of the ſorneth Verſe of the firſt Chapter of the firſt Book of the <hi>Kings</hi> declare) was ſo great, that the very Earth rent with the ſound that they made in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of it, can be compared to them. But I doubt you will ſcarce be ſo kind to your ſelves and them, as immediately to forſake your Sins, that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:36752:34"/>they may do this; you'll rather conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in them, and preſume upon the Mercies of God for pardon; but the Mercies of God are conditional, and you have no right to them, unleſs you perform the Condition. The wicked muſt forſake his way and the unrighteous Man his thoughts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the Lord, if he will have mercy and pardon: ontherwiſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have it; for Chriſt came not into the World to maintain people in ſin, but upon their Faith and Repentance to forgive them their Sins; this is the only way in which he will be a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our unto you, as you may learn from hes own Words, <hi>Luke</hi> the 7th. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, at the laſt Verſe. This you'll ſay you know very well, and that you muſt part with your ſins, or loſe Heaven; but you vainly think it's time enough yet, and ſo defer it from Day to Day, from Week to Week, and form Year to Year, 'till you are habituated to wickedneſs, and ſo make it the more difficult to caſt it off; and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36752:34"/>what if by deferring it thus from time to time, you ſhould be ſuddenly, as many are, taken out of the World, where are you then? I ſhall not ſpeak my thoughts, but leave you to judge what your place and your Portion muſt be for ever; very miſerable, I fear.</p>
            <p>For I muſt tell you, 'tis a great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and very dangerous for any one to think of doing that in time to come, which God bids him do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently; 'tis as if he knew better when it were to be done than God: And if God ſays, To day if you will hear his Voice, harden not your Hearts; and tells you, That this is the day in which you ſhould begin to ſeek after Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 2 Cor. 6.2. <hi>Behold now is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted time, behold, now is the day of Salvation;</hi> How dare you defer ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after it 'till to Morrow, much leſs for a longer time, as hereafter, as you call it? Is to this the ready way to provoke God to anger, and to make him Swear in his Wrath, as he did to <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:36752:35"/>ſtubborn <hi>Iſraelites, Pſalm</hi> the 95th. at the laſt Verſe, <hi>That you ſhall not enter into his Reſt?</hi> And then you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done to all Eternity. For, although God's Mercies are great, yet we muſt not careleſly and wilfully forget his Commands, and rely ſo much upon his Mercy, as to forget his Juſtice: for as he is merciful, ſo he is juſt; and a Man may run on in Wickedneſs ſo long till he becomes mercileſs, and then God's Juſtice will take hold on him, and deſtroy him, Jer. 13.14. <hi>And I'll daſh them one againſt another, even the Fathers and the Sons toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſays the Lord, I will not pity, nor ſpare, nor have mercy, but deſtroy them:</hi> And if you will prevent the paſſing of this dreadful Sentence upon you, now is the time. Seek ye the Lord whilſt he may be found, call ye upon him whilſt he is nigh. Conſider you have a whole Eternity to labour for, and you have, many of you, loſt a great deal of time already; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make the better uſe of what is to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36752:35"/>come, it may be ſhorter than you are aware of. Ask Forgiveneſs forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, under all the Circumſtances of Humility, on your bended knees, for all the Sins you have hitherto been ſhamefully guilty of, (for thoſe Knees, which are now too ſtrong to ply in God's Service, will be too weak one day to ſtand in his Preſence) and keep a ſtrict Account of all your Thoughts, Words, and Actions for the time to come, and every Night, before you compoſe your ſelves to ſleep, beſtow a little time in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how you have ſpent the day, and ſee what evil you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and what good you have omitted, that you may certainly and ſincerely crave Forgiveneſs for it; which is the propereſt and moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly method for getting into a Habit of Vertue and Goodneſs, eſpecially if you are careful to return Thanks to God in the Morning for preſerving of you from the perils of the Night,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36752:36"/>and earneſtly deſire that his Favour and Bleſſing may attend you through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Day, and that he would prevent your evil Actions, and bring your good ones to perfection: And not adventure to lie down in the Sins not only of that Day, but of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years, as too many careleſs Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do, 'tis much to be feared, leſt you ſhould ſleep the ſleep of Death, ſpoken of in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 13.3. and the Wrath of God ſhould ſeize upon you, and caſt you into the diſmal place of eternal miſery: But immediately fix your Reſolutions for the glorious Kingdom of everlaſting Happineſs, and let Piety be your continual pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, which is the certain way of attaining of it.</p>
            <p>Ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, and be not weary of it, but be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Followers of them that through Faith and Patience inherit the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; and in due ſeaſon you ſhall
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36752:36"/>reap your Reward, and be owned by Chriſt, when he comes in the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Father, with the Holy Angels, and appears to thoſe that look for him the ſecond time without ſin, unto Salvation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
